

SHEIKH BIN ENAM

SENIOR FULL STACK SOFTWARE ENGINEER

SPECIALIZED IN BACKEND DEVELOPMENT

PROFILE

I am an experienced Senior Full Stack Software Engineer specializing in developing backend solutions. Throughout my career, I have demonstrated leadership skills, fostered innovation, and successfully delivered complex applications. I am highly regarded for my understanding of software architecture and my commitment to staying up to date with the latest technologies.

CONTACT DETAILS

Address: Lansantie 3 E 54

02610 Espoo, Finland Phone: +358 41 725 89 28 saimulhq@gmail.com LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/saimulhg Github: github.com/saimulhq

Website: tinyurl.com/saimulhq

REFERENCE

Email:

Available upon request

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Developer

Visma Amplio Ltd. January 2024 - Present Project: Fikuro ERP

Description: Fikuro ERP serves SMEs in Finland, it allows users to record production, do warehouse transactions, create sales offers, sales orders and purchase orders, send invoices to various FMS systems and keep track of the stock.

Tools and platform: Spring Boot (Java 21), Angular, Typescript, MariaDB, RabbitMQ,

Amazon ECS, Docker, Github Actions, SonarQube

Responsibilities:

- Leading a team of six people
- Focusing on feature planning, design and architecture
- Focusing on backend development **REST APIs and feature development**
- Writing unit tests and integration tests
- Practicing Scrum within the team
- Responsible for creating event based solution for recording production using
- Fixing Sonarqube issues for the backend
- Guiding junior developers within the team
- Take part in release activities time to time
- Time to time upgrading 3rd party libraries being used in the backend
- Work on the UI when needed
- Using tools like Jira, Confluence, Slack and Google Meet
- **Senior Full Stack Software Engineer**

Nokia Solutions and Networks Ltd. (Espoo, Finland)

October 2021 - November 2023

Project: Nokia Orchestration OrderHub (Business Application)

Description: OrderHub is used to create different types of orders, managing and

monitoring orders and it is also used for managing manual tasks.

Tools and platform: Spring Boot (Java 17), ReactJS, TypeScript, MongoDB, Docker,

Kubernetes, Jenkins, SonarQube

Responsibilities:

- Focusing mainly on backend development
- **REST APIs and feature development**
- Writing unit tests and integration tests
- Practicing SAFe within team
- Responsible for migrating Java 11 to Java 17
- Responsible for migrating Spring Boot 2 to Spring Boot 3
- Acting as the lead product security expert
- Generating Anchor, Trivy, VAMS for detecting vulnerabilities and fixing them
- Fixing Sonarqube issues for the backend
- Guiding junior developers within the team
- Take part in release activities time to time
- Time to time upgrading 3rd party libraries being used in the backend
- Work on the UI when needed
- Using tools like Jira, Confluence, and Microsoft Teams

WORK EXPERIENCE (CONTINUED)

• Full Stack Software Developer

Tecnotree Corporation (Tampere, Finland)

August 2020 - September 2021

Project: Tecnotree Digital Resource Manager Bulk Processor

Description: Bulk processor is used for processing the creation, deletion, updation and bundling of digital resources (SIM, MSISDN, IP etc) in bulk and keep track of these generated resources (success, failures, reason of failure etc). On successful creation the bulk processor sends Kafka events, which other systems can listen to and perform actions based on it.

Tools and platform: ExpressJS, MongoDB, Apache Kafka, Docker, Protobuf, grpc, Jenkins, SonarQube **Responsibilites:**

- Focusing mainly on backend development
- Single-handedly worked on the the backend of the project from designing the architecture to coding, testing and deployment
- REST APIs and feature development
- Writing unit tests and integration tests
- Practicing Scrum within the team
- Responsible for TM Forum Open API certification for the product APIs
- Fixing Sonarqube issues for the backend
- Take part in release activities time to time
- Time to time upgrading 3rd party libraries being used in the backend
- Work on the UI when needed
- Using tools like Jira, Confluence, and Microsoft Teams
- Software Developer Trainee and Thesis Worker

Cloubi Ltd. [Part of Otava Publishing Company] (Tampere, Finland)

May 2019 - February 2020

Project: Cloubi Data Analytics Project

Description: It was developed for Cloubi and is used for generating the new data analytics report for the

teachers to view the overall performance of the students.

Tools and platform: Spring Boot (Java 8), Apache Kafka, MongoDB, Docker

Responsibilities:

- Single-handedly worked on the backend of the project as a proof of concept for my Master's Thesis
- Thesis title: Optimizing the Efficiency of the Data Analytics Framework Using Microservice
 Architecture
- REST APIs and feature development
- Writing unit tests and integration tests
- Practicing Scrum within the team
- Fixing Sonarqube issues
- Using tools like Jira, Confluence, Slack, and Google Meet
- Software Quality Assurance Engineer

Loence Solution (Dhaka, Bangladesh)

August 2017 - July 2018 Project: Loence ERP

Description: Manual software testing and had the opportunity to write automated tests of their main product which was an ERP system

Tools and platform: Selenium, Java

Responsibilities:

- Write automated test cases for the frontend using Selenium
- Perform manual testing of the features
- Practicing Scrum within the team
- Using tools like Trello, Slack, and Google Meet

Intern

Research and Development Team, Technology Division

bKash Ltd. (Dhaka, Bangladesh)

January 2016 - June 2016

Project: bKash Phonebook Directory

Description: It was developed for managing the contact details of bKash employees and was internally

used by bKash Ltd.

Platform and tools: Java EE, Oracle

Responsibilities:

- Single-handedly worked on the backend of the project from designing the architecture to coding and testing
- REST APIs and feature developmentWriting unit tests and integration tests
- Fixing Sonarqube issues
- Using tools like Jira, Confluence, Slack, and Google Meet

TECHNICAL COMPETENCIES

- Programming Language: Java, JS, Python, Go, C, C++, C#, PHP, R
- DevOps: Docker, Kubernetes, Gitlab-Cl, Jenkins, Github Actions, Rancher, SonarQube
- Version Control: Git, SVN
- **Web Development:** ReactJS, AngularJS, NodeJS, ExpressJS, Spring Boot, ASP.Net, Django, HTML, CSS, TS, Bootstrap, jQuery
- Database: Oracle, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Microsoft SQL, MariaDB, MongoDB
- Message Queing Service: Apache Kafka, RabbitMQ
- **Development Tools:** IntelliJ IDEA, Eclipse, Netbeans, Microsoft Visual Studio, Microsoft Visual Studio Code, PyCharm, CodeBlocks, QT Creator, RStudio
- Testing Tools: JUnit, Selenium, Mocha, Robot Framework
- Project Management Tools: Trello, Jira, Confluence
- Others: Microsoft Office

EDUCATION

Master of Science in Information Technology

Major: Software Engineering - Web & Cloud

Institution: Tampere University CGPA: 4.02 (on a scale of 5.00) Period: August 2018 - June 2020

Thesis Title: Optimizing the Efficiency of the Data Analytics Framework Using Microservice Architecture

Bachelor of Science in Software Engineering

Institution: University of Dhaka CGPA: 3.55 (on a scale of 4.00)

Period: January 2013 - December 2016

Project: Plagiar – A web-based plagiarism detecting tool that detects plagiarism from a selected repository and is a complete repository management system.

LANGUAGE SKILLS

English: FluentBangla: Native

• Finnish: Conversational (A2.2)